Ralph Ellison
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Writings File, 1935-1995, n.d. (Box 95-169)
  - Forewords, introductions, and endorsements (Box 109)
    - Romare Bearden: Paintings and Projections, The Art Gallery, State University of New York, Albany, N.Y., 1968-1969, n.d.
    - Valentine, Charles A., Culture and Poverty, 1967-1968
    - Walker, Scott, ed., Buying Time, 1985
  - Memoirs (Box 110)
    - Typescript draft, ca. 1981, (3 folders)
    - Draft fragments, n.d.
    - Notes and outlines, 1938, 1968, 1981-1985, n.d.
  - Miscellany
    - Bibliographies, 1968-1977, 1986, n.d., (2 folders)
    - Copyrights, 1963-1979, 1989
    - Literary criticism about Ellison
      - 1943-1959
      - 1960-1994, (7 folders) (Box 111)
      - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 112)
    - Notes, 1941-1988, n.d. See also Container 142, Invisible Man, (4 folders); (3 folders) (Box 113)
    - Permissions and reprints
      - 1956-1970, (5 folders)
      - 1971-1992, n.d., (4 folders) (Box 114)
    - Plot ideas, n.d.
    - Royalty statements, 1956-1958, 1964-1992 See also Oversize
    - Unidentified fragments, ca. 1940, 1963, n.d., (3 folders)
  - Novels (Box 115)
    - Airman novel, 1942-1945, n.d.
    - Hickman novel
      - Contract
      - Drafts
        - Episodes
          - "As Hickman Turned the Corner," n.d., (2 folders)
          - "Backwacking, A Plea to the Senator," 1976, n.d.
          - Bliss and Hickman at the circus, n.d. See also Container 116, Bliss, Body, and Meatwhistle
          - Bliss and Hickman at the movies, n.d.
          - Bliss and Severin's mother, n.d.
          - Bliss and Sister Georgia, n.d.
          - Bliss and the coffin, n.d. (Box 116)
          - Bliss, Body, and Meatwhistle, 1959, 1981, n.d. See also Container 115, Bliss and Hickman at the movies
          - Bliss recalls making the movie, n.d.
          - Bliss relates tale of Reverend Eatmore, n.d.
          - Bliss runs away to the moviehouse, n.d.
          - Bliss's kidnapping from church, n.d.
          - Briscoe and Silvester in the barbershop, n.d.
          - "Cave of the Winds," n.d.
          - "Charlee," n.d.
          - Cliofus and Miss Janey, n.d.
          - Cliofus describes "whooping," n.d., (1 folder) (Box 117)
          - "Cliofus Recalling Halloween," n.d.
          - Cliofus relates tale of "Big Mama and the Six Little Children" and Russian novel, 1982, n.d., (2 folders)
          - Cliofus relates tale of castration and the movie scene, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 118)
          - Cliofus relates tale of Miss Kindly and the whale, n.d. See also Container 130, "A Song of Innocence"
          - Cliofus relates tale of the elephant, 1983, n.d.
          - Cliofus talks with McIntyre, n.d., (3 folders)
          - Cliofus talks with Severin, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 119)
          - "Epigram for Novel," n.d.
          - Hickman and his congregation at the Lincoln Memorial, n.d.
          - Hickman and McIntyre: "How dare you force yourself into my secrets...," n.d.
          - Hickman and Milsap, n.d., (2 folders)
          - Hickman and Miss Janey, n.d.
          - Hickman and the birth of Bliss
            - 1965, 1976
            - 1985, n.d. (Box 120)
          - Hickman and Wilhite at Mister Jessie's, n.d.
            - Complete sequences, 1968, n.d., (6 folders)
            - Detective tells of scam, n.d.
            - Junk room, ca. 1985, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 121)
            - Lonnie Barnes's speech, 1972
            - Maud, the cross-eyed lady, n.d.
            - McMillen speaks to Hickman and Wilhite, 1976, 1990, n.d.
            - Miscellaneous scenes, n.d.
            - Police interrogate Hickman and Wilhite, n.d.
          - Hickman and Wilhite leave the Lincoln Memorial, n.d.
          - Hickman and Wilhite search for the senator's mistress, n.d. (Box 122)
          - Hickman arrives in Oklahoma, ca. 1987, n.d., (2 folders)
          - Hickman at Mr. Jessie's, n.d., (3 folders)
          - Hickman dreams about a funeral, n.d.
          - Hickman encounters Leroy, n.d, (2 folders) (Box 123)
          - "Hickman in Paris," 1989
          - "Hickman reaches decision to see Janey," n.d.
          - "Hickman Reminiscing," n.d., (3 folders) See also Container 124, "Ish Is Not a Fish"
          - Hickman studies the tapestry, n.d.
          - Hickman with Bliss at the hospital, n.d., (3 folders) See also Container 164, "Night Talk" (Box 124)
          - Hickman witnesses the shooting, n.d.
          - "Ish Is Not a Fish" and "Reconcilement," n.d. S ee also Container 123, "Hickman Reminiscing"
          - "It Always Breaks Out," n.d.
          - "Juneteenth," 1965, n.d.
          - LeeWillie and the car burning, n.d. See also Container 162, "Cadillac Flambé" (Box 125)
          - "Love. Two," 1987-1988, n.d., (3 folders)
          - McIntyre and Laura, n.d.
          - McIntyre at Mister Jessie's, n.d., (3 folders)
          - McIntyre in Salzburg, n.d. (Box 126)
          - McIntyre witnesses the shooting, n.d.
          - McIntyre's cousin, Gertrude, Buster, and the mother-in-law, n.d.
          - "McIntyre's Dream"
            - Hitching post boy, n.d.
            - Mother Strothers, 1971, n.d., (4 folders)
            - Sam, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 127)
          - McIntyre's letter from Vannec, n.d.
          - "Milsap's Report," n.d.
          - Miss Janey tells Hickman about the "smoking" incident, n.d.
          - Miss Janey's letter to Hickman, n.d.
          - Mother Strothers, n.d.
          - Mr. Love New, n.d.
          - Mr. Love New and Hickman, 1987-1988, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 128)
          - Mr. Love New and McIntyre, n.d.
          - Mr. Love New and Severin, n.d., (2 folders)
          - "Prologue," n.d., (5 folders) See also Container 162, "And Hickman Arrives" (Box 129)
          - "The Roof, the Steeple, and the People," n.d.
          - Senator and the Canadian River hunting party, n.d.
          - Senator's delirium, n.d., (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 130)
          - "The Senator's Practical Joke," n.d.
          - "The Senator's Secretary," n.d.
          - Severin and Cliofus as youths, n.d.
          - Severin and Miss Janey, n.d.
          - Severin and the shooting of the senator, n.d.
          - Severin in Europe, n.d.
          - "Severin Remembers," n.d.
          - "A Song of Innocence," 1978, n.d. See also Container 118, Cliofus relates tale of Miss Kindly and the whale, (2 folders)
          - Sunraider and the old gentleman, n.d. (Box 131)
          - Sunraider and the telephones, n.d.
          - "Sunraider Remembering," 1983
          - "Sunraider Visits a Hospital...," n.d.
          - Sunraider's speech on the Senate floor, n.d.
          - "They Beat You, Bliss," n.d.
          - "Through the Lilt and Tear," 1971, 1978, n.d., (3 folders)
          - "Uncle Bud with the Portable Radio," 1987, n.d.
          - Unidentified pages, n.d., (2 folders)
        - Original typescript (Box 132)
          - Book I, Apr. 1972, (3 folders)
          - Book II, 1972, (3 folders)
        - Revised typescript (Box 133)
          - Book I, July 1972, (2 folders)
          - Book II, July 1972, n.d., (3 folders)
        - Sequential fragments, 1990-1991, n.d., (1 folder); (6 folders) (Box 134, Box 135, Box 136, Box 137, Box 138)
      - Notes and notebooks, 1956-1989, n.d., (5 folders); (6 folders); (7 folders) (Box 139, Box 140, Box 141)
    - Invisible Man See also Container 113, Miscellaneous notes (Box 142)
      - Drafts
        - Episodes
          - "At Mary's," n.d., (2 folders)
          - "Bar Scene, Downtown," n.d.
          - "Bar Scene, El Toro," n.d.
          - "Battle Royal," n.d.
          - "Blind Man," n.d.
          - "Blues," also titled, "Something about Blues," n.d.
          - "Brockaway (Paint Factory)," n.d.
          - "Brotherhood," n.d., (1 folder); (5 folders) (Box 143)
          - "Brotherhood, Arena Speech," n.d.
          - "Brotherhood, Bear in Window," n.d.
          - "Brotherhood, Chtonian," n.d.
          - "Brotherhood, Clifton," n.d. See also Container 210, Times Square
          - "Brotherhood, Fired Tenement," n.d.
          - "Brotherhood, Louise," n.d.
          - "Campus," n.d., (2 folders) (Box 144)
          - "Chapel," first draft and notes, n.d.
          - "Cleo and Mt. Morris Park," n.d.
          - "Emerson," n.d.
          - "Eviction," n.d.
          - "Factory Hospital," n.d.
          - "Fat Man on a Bridge," n.d.
          - "Golden Day--True Blood," n.d.
          - "Harlem," n.d.
          - "Hattie and Julius Franklin," n.d.
          - "Hospital Alley Scene," also titled, "Nigger, What Kinda Man Am I?" n.d.
          - "Hospital and Escape," 1949
          - "Hospital and St. Mary's" (in continuity), n.d., (2 folders)
          - "Hospital Scene" (Box 145)
            - General, n.d., (3 folders)
            - Working copy, n.d.
          - "Jazz Music," n.d.
          - "Leroy's Journal," n.d.
          - "Lostness," n.d.
          - "Manhole," n.d.
          - "Men's House," n.d.
          - Miscellaneous scenes, n.d.
          - "Money Changers," n.d.
          - "New York," first draft and notes, n.d.
          - "New York Arrival," n.d.
          - "Norton in the Subway," n.d.
          - "Old Barbee," n.d.
          - "Paint Factory," n.d.
          - "Perception," original draft titled "Eviction, Priest, Parade, Party, Bank, and Apartment," n.d., (2 folders) (Box 146)
          - "Priest Scene," n.d.
          - "Prologue," n.d.
          - "Ras," n.d.
          - "Red Robe," n.d.
          - "Revenge in Mt. Morris Park," n.d.
          - "Rhinehart," n.d.
          - "Riot," n.d.
          - "Sea Cook," also titled, "One-Eyed Cook," n.d.
          - "Sybil," n.d
          - "Uncle Charles," n.d.
          - "Vet," n.d.
          - "Wheelchair," n.d.
          - "White Man in Harlem," n.d.
          - "Woodridge," n.d.
        - Original typescript, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 147)
        - Final typescript, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 148)
        - Corrected carbons (Box 149)
          - Set 1, n.d., (4 folders)
          - Set 2, n.d., (3 folders)
          - Set 3, n.d., (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 150)
        - Preface to the Franklin Library edition, ca. 1980
        - Foreword to thirtieth edition, 1982, n.d., (3 folders)
        - Fragments and partial drafts, 1951, n.d., (1 folder); (5 folders) (Box 151)
        - Notes, 1942-1950, n.d., (5 folders); (7 folders) (Box 152)
      - Author's first proof, 1951 See also Oversize
      - Uncorrected proof, 1952 (Box 153)
      - Blue lines for thirtieth edition, 1982
      - Film proposals, 1960-1971, 1978-1990, n.d., (2 folders)
      - Foreign rights and translations
        - 1952-1978
        - 1980-1989, n.d. (Box 154)
      - Literary agents, 1943-1953, 1989-1990, n.d.
      - Opera proposal, 1964-1965
      - Publicity, 1952-1953, 1981, 1992-1994, n.d.
      - Published editions
        - Franklin Library, 1976-1980, n.d.
        - New American Library of World Literature, 1951-1971, n.d.
        - Random House
          - Correspondence, 1947-1988, n.d., (2 folders)
          - Royalties, 1951-1980 See also Oversize
        - Westinghouse Learning Corp., 1970-1977, n.d. (Box 155)
      - Reviews
        - General, 1947-1955, 1964-1971, 1985, n.d., (6 folders)
        - Scrapbook, 1952, (2 folders)
      - Writings by others (Box 156)
        - Balmer, Simone, 1968
        - Bourrel, Anne-Marie, 1973
        - Brown, Daniel Webster, II, 1977
        - Ducornet, Guy, 1962
        - Giza, Joanne, 1972-1974, n.d.
        - Jordet, Brit Harstad, 1969
        - Mebane, Mary E., 1961
        - Miscellaneous authors, 1954, 1961-1982, n.d., (6 folders) (Box 157)
        - Reith, Emma A., n.d.
        - Thomas, Gwendolyn A., 1974 (Box 158)
        - Ulle, Carol H., 1971
    - Slick novel (Box 159)
      - Drafts
        - Episodes
          - Booker's reveries, n.d.
          - "Mister Mac" or "Tale of a Southern Road," n.d.
          - Slick and Booker above the drugstore, n.d.
          - Slick and Booker hunting, n.d.
          - Slick and Bostic, n.d.
          - Slick and Callie at the hospital, n.d.
          - Slick and Liles, n.d.
          - Slick and Lilly-Mae, n.d.
          - Slick and Snodgrass, n.d.
      - Original typescript, sections I and II, ca. 1939, (2 folders)
      - Miscellaneous pages, ca. 1939
      - Notes, n.d.
  - Poetry, 1935-1937, n.d., (2 folders)
  - Reviews
    - 1937-1939
    - 1940-1946, (10 folders) (Box 160)
    - 1947-1980, n.d., (8 folders) (Box 161)
  - Short stories (Box 162)
    - "Afternoon," n.d.
    - "And Hickman Arrives," 1959-1960 See also Container 129, "Prologue"
    - "Battle Royal," 1947-1948, 1975, n.d.
    - "The Birthmark," 1940, n.d.
    - "The Black Ball," n.d.
    - "Bullfighting," n.d.
    - "Butler Boy and the TV Set," n.d.
    - "Cadillac Flambé," 1972-1973, 1984 See also Container 125, LeeWillie and the car burning
    - "A Coupla Scalped Indians," 1956, n.d.
    - "Did You Ever Dream Lucky?" 1953, 1975, 1980, n.d.
    - "The Dream," 1941, n.d., (3 folders)
    - "Flying Home," 1944, 1971-1974, 1992, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 163)
    - "Gann Wilson," n.d.
    - "A Gari in Karachi," n.d.
    - "Goodnight Irene," n.d.
    - "A Hard Time Keeping Up" (posthumous title), n.d.
    - "Hymie's Bull" (posthumous title), n.d. See also Oversize
    - "I Did Not Learn Their Names," ca. 1940
    - "I'm in New York But New York Ain't in Me," n.d.
    - "In a Strange Country," also titled, "Black Yank in Britain," 1944, n.d.
    - "The Initiation," n.d., (5 folders) (Box 164)
    - "Jake Smith," n.d.
    - "The King of the Bingo Game," 1944, 1970-1974, 1980, 1988-1992, n.d.
    - "A Lament for Tod Clifton," This Is My Best (1970), 1968-1969
    - "Last Day," n.d.
    - "Mister Toussan," 1941-1947, 1971, n.d.
    - "Myth Mood," ca. 1937
    - "Night Talk," 1969 See also Container 124, Hickman with Bliss at the hospital
    - "Norman," 1983
    - Notes, 1978-1980, 1988-1990, n.d.
    - "Out of the Hospital and under the Bar," Soon, One Morning (1963), 1961-1968, n.d. (Box 165)
    - "Rabid Dog," n.d.
    - "The Red Cross at Morriston, Swansea, S.W.," n.d. See also same container, "A Storm of Blizzard Proportions"
    - "Sanctuary," n.d.
    - "Slick Gonna Learn," 1939
    - "A Song of Innocence," 1969-1971
    - "A Storm of Blizzard Proportions," 1944, n.d. See also same container, "The Red Cross at Morriston, Swansea, S.W."
    - "That I Had the Wings," n.d., (3 folders)
    - Tillman and Tackhead, n.d., (3 folders)
    - "You Can't Get Around It," n.d. (Box 166)
    - Untitled, n.d., (3 folders)
  - Writings by others
    - Bone, Robert, 1972
    - Burgest, David R., 1980
    - Callahan, John F., 1977, 1995, n.d.
    - Crouch, Stanley, 1986, n.d.
    - Eckels, Jon, 1972 (Box 167)
    - Hyman, Stanley Edgar, 1946, 1970, n.d.
    - Jenkins, Betty, and Susan Phillis, 1973
    - Long, Charles H., 1971-1976
    - Lucas, John, 1981-1988
    - McKay, W. Colin, 1993
    - McPherson, James Alan, n.d.
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1936-1989, (2 folders)
      - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 168)
    - Mooreland, Marc, 1969-1974
    - Murray, Albert, n.d.
    - Oden, Gloria C., 1976
    - Piel, Gerard, 1974
    - Rodman, Selden, 1971
    - Schor, Edith, 1973, (2 folders)
    - Scott, Nathan A., 1963-1966, 1979-1989, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 169)
    - Stuckey, Elma, 1975
    - Thomas, Bettye J., 1986
    - Thorne, Hillery C., Jr., 1977
    - Ward, Theodore, n.d.
    - Webb, Constance, 1966-1967
    - Wright, Richard, n.d.
    - Yust, Larry, 1971, n.d.
- Speeches, Lectures, and Interviews, 1945-1993, n.d. (Box 170-178)
  Texts of speeches, lectures, and interviews along with related correspondence, notes, and printed matter.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Speeches (Box 170)
    - 1953, 27 Jan., acceptance speech, National Book Award, New York, N.Y., 1953, n.d.
    - 1963, 5 Sept., "What These Children Are Like," Seminar on Education for Culturally Different Youth, 1963-1965, n.d., (3 folders)
    - 1964, 1 Apr., National Institute of Arts and Letters, New York, N.Y., 1964
    - 1965
      - [May], presentation of Howells Medal to John Cheever, American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, New York, N.Y., n.d.
      - Aug.-Sept., scripts for National Educational Television, "Arts USA: Music," 1965
    - 1966, 26 May, American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, New York, N.Y., 1966
    - 1968, 6 Nov., "The Uses of History in Fiction," Southern Historical Association, New Orleans, La., 1968 See also Container 108, "The Uses of History in Fiction"
    - 1970, 23 Feb., remarks on Duke Ellington, NAACP, New York, N.Y., 1969-1970, n.d.
    - 1972, 4 June, commencement address, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Va., 1972, n.d., (2 folders)
    - 1974, 12 June, address to class of 1949, Associated Harvard Alumni, Cambridge, Mass., 1974, 1992 See also Container 214, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. (Box 171)
    - 1975
      - 10 May, "The Little Man Behind the Stove," Curtis Institute of Music, Philadelphia, Pa., 1974-1978, n.d., (4 folders)
      - 21 June, dedication speech, Ralph Ellison Branch, Metropolitan Library System, Oklahoma City, Okla., 1975
    - 1976
      - 28 Apr., "American Music: A Personal Glance after Two Hundred Years," Society for the Libraries, New York University, New York, N.Y., 1976
      - 30 Apr., "Perspective of Literature," School of Law, New York University, New York, N.Y., 1975-1976, n.d.
    - 1978, 17 May, introduction of newly-elected members, American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, New York, N.Y., n.d.
    - 1979, 19 Sept., Ralph Ellison Festival, Brown University, Providence, R.I., 1979-1980, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 172)
    - 1983, 18 May, presentation of Gold Medal for Fiction to Bernard Malamud, American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, New York, N.Y., 1966-1973, 1979-1983, n.d., (2 folders)
    - 1988, 6 Apr., "Bearden," Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine, New York, N.Y., 1988
    - 1992, "Intellectuals and Writers Since the Thirties," Partisan Review conference, 1992, n.d.
    - 1993, Apr., American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1993
  - Lectures
    - 1945, 1 Nov., "American Negro Writing, A Problem of Identity," Bennington College, Bennington, Vt., 1945, n.d.
    - 1953
      - 27 May, "Invisible Man," Hunter College, New York, N.Y., 1953
      - 3-5 Aug., class on the contemporary novel, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., 1952-1954, n.d. See also Container 107, "Twentieth Century Writing and the Black Mask of Humanity"
    - 1954 (Box 173)
      - Aug.-Sept., "The Role of the Novel in Creating the American Experience," Salzburg Seminar in American Studies, Salzburg, Austria, 1953-1955, 1961-1966, 1976, n.d., (4 folders)
      - Sept.-Oct., Symposium on North American Studies, El Escorial, Spain, 1954
    - 1969
      - 26 Mar., lecture on Invisible Man, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y., 1968-1974, n.d., (3 folders)
      - 18 Apr., "The Negro Writer: His Contributions, His Problems," Lafayette College, Easton, Pa., 1968-1969 (Box 174)
    - 1971, 18 July, "Remembering Richard Wright," University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, 1971-1972, n.d., (2 folders) See also Container 105, "Remembering Richard Wright"
    - Undated
      - Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y.
      - "Hidden Name and Complex Fate," Library of Congress
      - "The Meaning of American Diversity," Oberlin College, Oberlin, Ohio
      - New York University, New York, N.Y., (2 folders)
      - University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
  - Interviews
    - 1952, Denver Post, Denver, Colo., 1952
    - 1953, 8 Feb., "Faulkner, The Bear," radio broadcast, Irving Howe and Lyman Bryson, 1953
    - 1955, "Ralph Ellison, The Art of Fiction," Paris Review, Spring 1955, (3 folders) (Box 175)
    - 1960, 11 May, "A Talk with Ralph Ellison," Richard G. Stern, 1960-1961, n.d.
    - 1964, "An Interview with Ralph Ellison," Allen Geller, Tamarack Review, Summer 1964
    - 1965
      - May, Umbra, 1965-1966, n.d., (2 folders)
      - 4-18 Nov., National Educational Television, 1965
      - Pierre Dommergues, 1965-1967
      - Richard Kostelanetz, 1965, 1989, n.d.
      - Who Speaks for the Negro? Robert Penn Warren, 1964-1965, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 176)
    - 1966
      - 1 Feb., National Educational Television, 1966
      - 30 Aug., United States Senate, Subcommittee on Reorganization of the Committee on Government Operations, 1966-1967, n.d., (3 folders)
    - 1967
      - Mar., "A Very Stern Discipline," Harper's Magazine, 1966-1967, n.d., (4 folders)
      - May, America (Russian edition), 1967 (Box 177)
      - Radio broadcast, WGBH, Boston, Mass., Richard H. Lee, 1966-1967
    - 1969, "Ralph Ellison, La Invisibilidad del Negro y el Pluralismo Cultural," Esther Tusquets, Triunfo, Spring 1969
    - 1970, "The Scholar's Bookshelf," radio broadcast, John Graham, 1970-1973, n.d.
    - 1971, 30 Sept., "Ralph Ellison, 20 Years After," David L. Carson, 1971-1974, n.d., (3 folders)
    - 1972
      - Dec., "Interview with Ralph Ellison," John O'Brien
    - ca. 1972, John Hersey, 1972-1973, n.d.
    - 1976
      - 27 Jan., "Interview with Ralph Ellison," Ron Welburn, Grackle, 1976-1977
      - 7 Mar., "Ralph Ellison: An Interview," Michael S. Harper and Robert B. Stepto, 1975-1977, n.d., (2 folders)
      - "An Interview with Ralph Ellison: Visible Man," Howard Sage, Pulp, Summer 1976 (Box 178)
      - Ishmael Reed, Steve Cannon, and Quincy Troupe, Yardbird Reader, 1976-1978, n.d., (2 folders)
    - 1982
      - Oct., Playboy, 1982
      - No month, John Hersey, 1982, n.d.
    - Undated, "An Interview with Ralph Ellison," N. A. Samstag and Ted Cohen, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous notes and fragments, ca. 1940, 1954-1960, 1966-1969, n.d., (4 folders)
- Reference File, 1901-1995, n.d. (Box 179-211)
  Printed matter, primarily newspaper and magazine clippings, on topics of interest to Ellison, such as jazz, blues, photography, art, and prominent individuals.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute, New York, N.Y., 1969-1972, n.d. (Box 179)
  - Abortion, 1983, 1993
  - Africa, 1943-1989 See also Oversize
  - African-American leadership, 1943-1981
  - African-American organizations, 1972-1989
  - African-American studies, 1917, 1940-1994, n.d., (2 folders) See also Oversize
  - American Indians, 1949-1993, n.d. See also Oversize
  - Animals, 1936-1982, n.d.
  - Anti-Semitism, 1939-1992, n.d.
  - Architecture and interior design, 1948-1987, n.d. (Box 180)
  - Art
    - African art, 1970-1992, n.d.
    - Catalogs, 1947, 1959-1982, n.d., (2 folders)
    - Institute of Negro Art, 1929
    - Miscellany, 1937-1991, n.d., (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 181)
    - Sculpture, 1951-1973, n.d.
  - Audio equipment and technology, 1940-1958, n.d.
  - Biographical information
    - Agee, James, 1949-1991, n.d.
    - Ali, Muhammad (Cassius Clay), 1963-1969
    - Anderson, Marian, 1958-1993, n.d.
    - Armstrong, Louis, 1954-1983
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1949-1989, n.d.
    - Baker, Josephine, 1950-1994
    - Baldwin, James, 1953, 1971-1994, n.d.
    - Baraka, Imamu Amiri (LeRoi Jones), 1964-1968, 1983-1990, n.d.
    - Barry, Marion, 1988-1990 (Box 182)
    - Bearden, Romare, 1967-1981, 1991, n.d.
    - Bellow, Saul, 1953, 1970-1987
    - Berryman, John, 1972, 1982
    - Branam, Virgil, 1973
    - Brown, Lewis Thomas, 1979-1980
    - Burke, Kenneth, 1959-1987, n.d.
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1935-1990, n.d., (3 folders)
    - Chambers, Whittaker, and Alger Hiss, 1930, 1948-1952, 1970, n.d.
    - Cheever, John, 1968-1982, n.d. (Box 183)
    - Clarke, Kenneth Bancroft, 1973-1985, n.d.
    - Cleaver, Eldridge, 1968-1976
    - Cowley, Malcolm, 1939-1947, 1973, 1989
    - Crouch, Stanley, 1980-1991, n.d.
    - "C" miscellaneous, 1936-1993, n.d., (3 folders)